Guide to the Consumer Reports. Irving Michelson papers, 1942-1981 and undated RL.11819
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Irving Michelson papers
1942-1981 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11819
3.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Irving Michelson was a chemist who directed the Special Projects and Public Service Projects departments during the 1950s-1960s. The Irving Michelson papers include clippings, correspondence, reprints of articles, research data, questionnaires, reports and other printed materials. Topics include air pollution, cigarette testing, economics, nuclear radiation and fallout, packaging standards, and seat belt design and testing. Much of the research discussed in the papers was conducted in Connecticut. Organizations represented include the British Consumers Association, Consumers Union, International Organization of Consumers' Unions, and the U.S. Defense Department. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General Files; Air Pollution; Nuclear Radiation/Fallout; Seat Belts
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Irving Michelson was a chemist who directed the Special Projects and Public Service Projects departments during the 1950s-1960s.
Irving Michelson was born in 1911 in New York. He graduated from Brooklyn College (BS chemistry, 1939). Michelson worked at the U.S. Naval Observatory (1930-1936) and the U.S. Customs Laboratory (1936-1947) before joining Consumers Union. Michelson served as head of the Chemical Division (1947-1952) and Special Projects Division (1952-1957) before being named Assistant Director of the Technical Division in 1957. In 1959 Michelson became Director of the Public Service Projects Division where he remained until he left Consumers Union in 1964 to become Director of Scientific Research at the America Safety Equipment Corporation. Michelson retired in 1976 and died in 2013.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Irving Michelson papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports. Advocacy records
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Board of Directors records
Consumer Reports. Eileen Nic papers
Consumer Reports. Washington Office records
J. Walter Thompson Company. Information Center vertical files
J. Walter Thompson Company. Wallace W. Elton papers
Richard Pollay Tobacco Industry Promotion (TIPS) collection
Collection Overview
The Irving Michelson papers include clippings, correspondence, reprints of articles, research data, questionnaires, reports and other printed materials. Topics include air pollution, cigarette testing, economics, nuclear radiation and fallout, packaging standards, and seat belt design and testing. Much of the research discussed in the papers was conducted in Connecticut. Organizations represented include the British Consumers Association, Consumers Union, International Organization of Consumers' Unions, and the U.S. Defense Department.
consumer protection; Consumer advocacy; Pollution; Pollution -- Economic aspects; Nuclear energy; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Michelson, Irving
- General Files, 1942-1981; 1
  - Alcohol--Statement at Standard-of-Fill hearing, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Articles, 1942-1971 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes: Comparative Method for Studying Costs of Air Pollution; Dynamic Tests of Restraining Devices for Automobile Passengers; Environmental Pollution by Radiation; Fallout in Food; Radioactivity in the Total Diet; Radioisotopes in the 1962, 1963, 1964 Diet; Radium-226 in the Total Diet; Selected Results from Total Diet Studies; Strontium-90 in the Total Diet; The Chemist's Ethic and the Community; The Determinatino of Vegetable Matter Content of Wool; The Distribution of Cut Fiber Lengths in Wool Sampled by Cylindrical Tube Borings; The Public and Air Pollution Control
  - Biographical material, 1952-1974 (Box 1)
  - Cigarettes--Test methods international correspondence, 1962-1964 (Box 1)
  - Consumers Union public service projects, 1963-1972 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1957-1965, 1977-1981; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - IOCU (International Organization of Consumers' Unions), 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - U.S. Department of Defense project, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    Studies of military exchanges, antifreeze; unsafe products
- Air Pollution, 1959-1971 and undated; 2
  - Connecticut Clean Air Task Force, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Conference on Clean Air, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut work sheets, 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut work sheets, 1967-1968 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Box 2)
  - Costs of air pollution report files, 1964-1965; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Economic costs--Data tabulation, undated (Box 2)
  - Economic costs--Validation study, 1967 (Box 3)
  - Economic effects, 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - Economic effects--Documents, 1960-1967 (Box 3)
  - Economic effects--Interest, 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Hair and facial care questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 3)
  - Health questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 3)
  - Laundry questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 3)
  - Local area calculations, approximately 1959 (Box 3)
    Includes: Kansas City; New York-New Jersey metropolitan; Upper Ohio River Valley; Washington, D.C.
  - New York City Council hearing, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Office maintenance questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 4)
  - Papers, 1960-1969; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Replies to requests for information from cities, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Report graphs, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Requests for information, 1967-1971 (Box 4)
  - Requests for report, 1962-1965 (Box 4)
  - Residential maintenance questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 4)
  - Steubenville study, 1960; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Steubenville study, 1960 (Box 8)
  - Store operations questionnaire, approximately 1959 (Box 4)
  - Washington, D.C. pollution conference, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Wien report draft, part 1, undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    Armour Research Foundation-funded project
- Nuclear Radiation/Fallout, 1960-1971; 3
  - American Public Health Association meeting, 1969 (Box 5)
  - Fallout in the 1963 Teenage Diet (Box 5)
  - National Institutes of Health (NIH) grant correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 5)
  - New Rochelle City Council hearing on Davids Island, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Papers, 1960-1969 (Box 5)
- Seat Belts, 1942-1970; 4
  - General Files, 1961-1970; 1
    - British Consumers Association--European tests, 1961-1963 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence--Bertil Aldman, 1962-1968 (Box 5)
    - Economic Commission for Europe, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - Federal standards, 1963-1966 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1961-1964; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Standards--Society of Automotive Engineers (SAE)/International Standards Organization (ISO), 1965-1970; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Test Methods, 1942-1967; 2
    - General, 1957-1963 (Box 6)
    - Australia, 1961-1963 (Box 6)
    - California, 1957-1967 (Box 6)
    - Canada, 1962-1964 (Box 6)
    - France (in French), 1967 (Box 6)
    - General Services Administration, 1958-1962 (Box 6)
    - Germany (in German), 1962 (Box 6)
    - Great Britain, 1962-1963 (Box 6)
    - Great Britain, 1962-1963 (Box 8)
    - Hickok brand, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Holland, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
    - Holland, 1963-1964 (Box 8)
    - J.T. Muller Dynamic Testing, 1942-1962 (Box 7)
    - New Jersey Dynamic Testing Laboratory, 1963 (Box 7)
    - Sweden (in English and Swedish), 1957-1967 (Box 7)